<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<chapter id = "testpage_print">
  <title>Test Page Printing</title>
  <para>
The queues are saved when finishing the printer module.
When testing printer, only the queue being tested is saved. The names of these
saved queues are <computeroutput>y2test</computeroutput>,
or <computeroutput>y2testNUMBER</computeroutput> (first free number is found
in order to avoid collision of queue names). The problem may
occur when tested queue is somehow connected to other queue that hasn't
been saved yet (eg. create a queue A and then create a queue B which will
be a network queue forwarding jobs to the queue A of the local host which 
hasn't been saved.
  </para>
  <para>
After a queue is saved, the test page is prepared. There are two kinds of
test pages: ASCII test page and PostScript test page.
  </para>
  <section id="ascii_testpage">
    <title>ASCII Test Page</title>
    <para>
There is no need to update the ASCII test page before being printed.
It is just passed to the spooler.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="postscript_testpage">
    <title>PostScript Test Page</title>
    <para>
There are two possibilities how to print the PostScript test page: With a
high color photography and without it. The reason is that some PostScript
printers may fail printing this high color photography without the job
being processed by ghostscript.
    </para>
    <para>
Before the test page is printed, the graphics and texts are patched into
it via an external script. The graphics contain the vendor logo and a photo
for testing photographic printing. Texts contain all texts in the test page
(so that the page can be localized). Currently, only
<computeroutput>ASCII</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>ISO-8859-1|2|15</computeroutput> encodings are supported.
The queue name, printer vendor and model, PPD file nick name, printer
URI, location description, information and options as adjusted in the
PPD file are patched to the test page too.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
